<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>{&quot;en&quot;=&gt;&quot;Tangible Choreography&quot;, &quot;ja&quot;=&gt;&quot;タンジブル・コリオグラフィ&quot;}</title>
    <description>{&quot;en&quot;=&gt;&quot;A blog of the Tangible Choreography project&quot;, &quot;ja&quot;=&gt;&quot;タンジブル・コリオグラフィのブログ&quot;}</description>
    <link>http://tangiblechoreography.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://tangiblechoreography.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 10:20:18 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 10:20:18 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>コリオグラフィの具現化</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;私、稗田直人は日本で電気電子工学を学び、メディア・アーティストとしてカナダのモントリオールで活動しています。修士課程在籍時は顔面のプロジェクション・マッピングなどインタラクティブな作品をＩＶＲＣ（東京、2014年）やラヴァル・バーチャル（フランス、2015年）等で発表してきました。当時の作品の多くはキネクトなどのセンサを用いて体の動きを測定し、エンタテインメントやアートに活用することを目的としていました。また、できるだけ他の研究者たちが取り組んでいない体の部位をテーマにプロジェクションをすることを考えている中で顔という部位を選びました（もちろん、すでに&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=na7FU-VTWN8&quot;&gt;真鍋大度氏・ザック・リーバーマン氏&lt;/a&gt;や&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/103425574&quot;&gt;浅井宣通氏&lt;/a&gt;がすばらしい作品を発表しています）。しかし、&lt;a href=&quot;http://choreographiccoding.org/&quot;&gt;コリオグラフィック・コーディング・ラボ（ＣＣＬ）&lt;/a&gt;でコンテンポラリー・ダンスの考え方について学び、&lt;a href=&quot;http://neurotechx.com/&quot;&gt;NeuroTechX&lt;/a&gt;で神経科学について触れていく中でもっと抽象的な概念、すなわち動きの考え方について取り組みたいと考えるようになりました。そしてタンジブル・コリオグラフィを立ち上げるに至ったのですが、その裏には技術によってコリオグラフィの考え方を体以外の方法で表現することはできないかというアイデアがあります。次回以降に述べるように、このプロジェクトはコリオグラファ、ダンサー、技術者、観客のすべてに貢献することを目的としています。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;コンテンポラリー・ダンスやコンテンポラリー・アートでは動きや見た目を唯一の成果としているのではなく、作品に秘められたアイデアや疑問、あるいはその作品を通じて観客と対話をすること目的となっていることがしばしばあります。また、オマージュであったりストーリーが隠されていたりと、パフォーマンスでは語られない部分があることもしばしばあります。これらは、パフォーマンスだけを見ることで作品を理解しようと思っている人たちにとっては作品を楽しむ上での障害となるでしょう。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一方でメディア・アートはテクノロジーを用いた芸術のことで、マイクロ・コントローラやカメラ、バイオ・センサなどのセンサの発達により観客が体験することができ、予備知識がなくとも理解しやすい作品が多くあります。また、映像や音に限らず、物理的なインターフェースを用いることで触ること、触られることが可能な作品もあります。もしコンテンポラリー・ダンスやアートが疑問や対話を主題としているのであれば、メディア・アートによってパフォーマーと観客の対話を手助けすることができると私は考えています。ここで私が提案しているのはテレパシー装置やオーディオ・ガイドを開発するということではありません。むしろパフォーマンスのデリケートな部分を保ったまま、言葉を用いずに観客にアイデアを届けることが重要だと考えています。そのためにはアルゴリズムをより賢くしなくてはなりません。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tangiblechoreography.org/2016/05/05/%E3%82%B3%E3%83%AA%E3%82%AA%E3%82%B0%E3%83%A9%E3%83%95%E3%82%A3%E3%81%AE%E5%85%B7%E7%8F%BE%E5%8C%96.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tangiblechoreography.org/2016/05/05/%E3%82%B3%E3%83%AA%E3%82%AA%E3%82%B0%E3%83%A9%E3%83%95%E3%82%A3%E3%81%AE%E5%85%B7%E7%8F%BE%E5%8C%96.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Materializing Choreography</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a Japanese media artist residing in Montreal, Canada with a background in engineering. I have created bizarre interactive installations such as face projection mapping selected to IVRC 2014 (Japan) and Laval Virtual 2015 (France). These projects involve motion sensors (e.g., Microsoft Kinect) and are focused on how to use tracked body movements for entertainment or art. I always had an idea to augment a body part that people rarely do, and therefore I chose face projection (although there are some great works already exist, for example, by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=na7FU-VTWN8&quot;&gt;Daito Manabe and Zach Lieberman&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/103425574&quot;&gt;Nobumichi Asai&lt;/a&gt;). However, as I learned ideas behind contemporary dance at a &lt;a href=&quot;http://choreographiccoding.org/&quot;&gt;Choreographic Coding Lab&lt;/a&gt; and am involved in the neuroscience community through &lt;a href=&quot;http://neurotechx.com/&quot;&gt;NeuroTechX&lt;/a&gt;, I had a desire to tackle with something more abstract: ideas behind movements. This is the reason why I launched &lt;em&gt;Tangible Choreography&lt;/em&gt;, and the aim is to materialize choreographic ideas by technologies in addition to a human body. As I will describe later in this series, the project will contribute to choreographers, dancers, engineers, computer scientists, and audiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contemporary dance and contemporary art involves questions, ideas, and most importantly, communication between performers and audiences. In that sense, these ideas may not be expressed explicitly in the movement or appearance. Also a piece can be homage or accompanies a story behind it, as any other kinds of art do, which may not be explained during the performance. This is a barrier to appreciate a piece for those who are expecting that the piece is self-contained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, media art is a form of art, often interactive for audiences and intuitive to understand, using technologies, such as computers, microcontrollers, robots and sensors including cameras and bio/neuro sensors. It does not only provide audiovisual experiences but can employ physical materials to touch or to be touched. If contemporary dance [art] is about questions and relationships, I am sure that media art can help communication between a performer and an audience through forms or modalities that are not limited to audio and visual. I must note that I am not inventing a telepathy-like device that explicitly delivers what performers are thinking to audiences. However, my goal is to encourage audiences to understand ideas in an implicit way that does not interrupt the performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tangiblechoreography.org/2016/05/05/materializing-choreography.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tangiblechoreography.org/2016/05/05/materializing-choreography.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
